人數噉就開會啦。誒，有請政府同埋調評會嘅嘅代表。
就噉。
就散，就散。
早晨咁多位，咁誒或者我有請政府嘅代表誒。
阿李生，講一講我哋誒，你哋遞咗一份文件上嚟，CB四一五一slash十二hiven十三。
噉就我哋同事都應該睇咗㗎啦，咁或者你可以好簡短噉樣講一講呢份文件，補充下，跟住我哋就有請啊調評會嘅嘅嘅主席去講幾句説話。
嗯，早晨主席啊，早晨議員，多謝主席哈。
就誒，我哋份文件就係誒回應咗上一次我哋開會之後收到議員嘅提問。
噉我哋主要就係畀咗啲數字，依啲數字咧就係去到啊，我哋交份文件嗰日係準確嘅噉。咁見見到啲數字就啊。
係接近係誒，當然有有啲當然有一啲嘅調解員咧，佢係喺不同嘅啊附表都有佢嘅名喺度嘅。噉啊，見到而家我哋都係係有千多個嘅調解員喺香港嘅啦。
咁另外嘅。
機構佢哋作嘅資格評審咧，就誒，因為佢哋未有公開嘅記錄，咁變咗我哋唔好意思，我哋畀唔到一啲誒，我哋認為係準準確嘅數字畀大家。
咁呢啲我哋其實呢個亦都係其中個原因，我哋點解覺得有一個單一嘅資格評審組織會係好好多等等。
啊！誒，關於係誒阿梁議員佢嘅要求，話我哋係。
將嗰佢嗰個信息帶畀係誒。
香港誒調解資格評入。
啊！
組織誒Hong Kong Mail嘅話咧，我哋已經係做咗呢一樣嘢啦嚇。
其他我哋喺第五至到第九段咧，我哋就列出我哋嗰時係認為係要啊條例生效之前需要完成嘅準備工作。
噉係大部分咧，我哋都做咗㗎啦，主席嚇。咁如果議員有啲乜嘢嘅提問，我哋可以提問，我哋可以回答嘅噉。
啊，Mr. Bush。
We would like to hear from you now about.
your views on the government's paper and also in the last meeting which you were not here, members discussed the the readiness of Hong Kong mail in in
setting up the scheme and and your office and etcetera, maybe you can give us your views on that. Thank you.
Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Thank you for inviting me. This is my first time to this wonderful building.
嗯。
我係被working very closely with the administration on the creation of Hong Kong Mall。我諗，如果你哋aware，我係被involved in the mediation movement in Hong Kong for many years。
And in particular with regard to accreditation, I at present chair the accreditation committee of the Hong Kong International Arbitration Centre. I'm also
on various other committees, the judiciary's working party, and I have also been very much involved in in the mediation movement in Hong Kong. And my particular interest is in accreditation. And I would be the first to say that I was delighted the day that Hong Kong Ma was was we got her certificate of.
corporation。
We still got quite a bit of work to do. As you know, we have a
A body which has been formed, which we believe with the four premier.
bodies that have got, we believe the most accredited mediators in Hong Kong, whose standards are of course very high, and that is something that we feel very strongly about.
嗯。
我成為 inaugural chairman of this body， and we have.
It is an industry-led body.
and therefore we
do not have any public funding for this body, and we considered that the most economic way to start.
should I wait? Oh no, please.
The best way forward for us, bearing in mind that we are not a drain on the public resources, we are not asking for any funding. It's an industry-led body. That the best way forward would be to seek assistance from one of the bodies in the.
H.K. Mall to be the secretariat to start us off.
We have actually received three submissions to be the secretariat from the Hong Kong Mediation Centre, from the HKIAC, and also from the Law Society. And bearing in mind there are only four founder members, I therefore decided that we were three of us were in conflict.
利益，所以我問主席，巴先生羅曼諾斯，問。
work with Mr Simon Lee and his team to put together.
啊，呢～
Basically, a paper.
Giving their views as to which of the three bids we should go with, so I'm waiting for that paper. But I believe it's quite well advanced. But we are now in the middle of November, and originally we had thought that we would start by the 1st of January. I'm not sure at the present moment. I can't give any commitment to this.
committee this morning that we will be able to go live on with accreditation on the first of January.
Because there's still quite a lot of work to do. I mean, I'm basically doing it all pro bono at the present moment, and I'm quite happy to do that. But at the present moment, like every body that starts up, it's got quite a lot of things to do. I mean, we must set up a website, we must meet a lot to.
ensure that that we do not have a false start, so I'm not sure that we will be beginning on on the first of January now, but I I don't see any association between the mediation ordinance commencement date and HK Mall. I mean, there was at one time in the draft bill a mention of HK.
That came out at quite an early stage, and so I think we need to.
我 mean you need to think anyway about is there any association between these two things? and I would say there's not. We are very keen to ensure that HKML is the primary accreditation body in Hong Kong, and
We can only do that because we've got no ordinance backing. We can only do that in by
grandfathering in those that seek to apply to Concor Mall, and we're not saying that everybody will apply, and there's also we know a great deal of double counting between the various accreditation bodies.
所以，我我 have read， and I don't disagree with the administration's paper which you have before you.
Thank you, Mr. Butch。啊，議員有啊，何秀蘭議員。誒，主席啊，到最後咧，即係業界都有好多事情要做嘅，因為誒，我哋而家準確人數唔知啦，誒，有不同嘅團體都話自己係可以培訓到調解員啦。咁如果
我哋想誒呢個角色係可以到最後有質素保證啊！大家都有一個最基本嘅認可嘅資格咧。咁其實就算呢條條例生效，可以保護到一啲資料或者嗰個運作過程裏邊誒一啲嘅誒。
嗯。
相關嘅人或者資料都好啦，但係對整個業界嚟講，誒要做到嗰個質素保證同埋誒支撐到呢個調評會嘅運作係需要一段時間。噉，主席，我我想問政府，佢自己喺將來嗰個調評會嘅發展同埋。
業界嘅發展嗰度，佢仲有冇承擔嘅咧？呢個其一，其二咧就係其實而家我知道有啲大學咧，亦都開緊課程嘅添。咁未知大學而家誒專上教育產業化啦，噉啊大學梗係希望好多人去讀啦，但係同。
調評會，誒幾個誒誒創會嘅會員，大家有冇溝通咧？會唔會將來係發生到有啲同學，或者係已經係執緊業嘅社工或者其他行業嘅人？
讀完啦，但係又冇獲得資格，會唔會有啲噉嘅事情出現咧？
啊，李生，我請你啊，李生答先。
主席嚇，就當然係誒調解喺香港一路咁發展嘅。我哋而家做誒個推廣咧，係完全我哋係唔係話影響到個發展？我哋係支持同埋係希望更加令到個發展咧係好向好個方面進行噉樣。咁成立誒。
呢個調評會係其中一部。
但係最重要一步咧，我哋見到咧就係話係，亦都受到好多誒嘅業界嘅支持，就係有呢個條例。因為呢個條例就係畀到個基礎，我哋用一個更加好嘅基礎去進行調解。啊，噉我哋係就寫定出就係關於係保密啊，關於係誒幾時可以披露向法庭披露啊噉樣呢？
啲係好重要嘅，我哋認為一個環節係去推廣調解。
噉係調平會當然有佢嘅發展。頭先聽到啊啊啊，Mr. John Batch佢對啊調平會嘅工作嘅進度嘅意見。
噉我哋亦都係喺政府咧，我哋係都希望亦都係推廣到呢一樣嘢。啊，如果係有有啊。
我哋唔係話係誒，我哋都係。
係關注呢個發展係點樣做法，我哋都知道係業界咧，亦都係等緊睇下我哋點樣去直接參與呢個調評會嘅工作，同埋加入個調評會噉樣。
咁呢個係進行緊嘅，誒，關於係大學課程啊，其他嗰啲咧，咁呢一個咧係誒，我哋亦都有留意緊，係係點樣佢哋嗰個進展係如何，咁渠道係溝通咧，肯定就有喺度嚇，噉係誒。
大學同埋調評會咧，係可以大家直接溝通嘅嚇。
主席啊，係誒一就係，我不如講得白啲咧。政府會唔會畀一筆種子基金過去呢個調評會嗰度，等佢可以即係整一個秘書處啊，去誒盡快加快去做呢啲資格認可啊各樣，因為誒其他嘅專業自我規管嘅組織咧。
噉佢哋因為歷史悠久，噉就誒加入呢個專業，噉佢會誒誒啊呢個註冊啊各樣啊，都要畀一筆錢去支撐住呢個自我規管嘅組織。咁但係調解員，因為係新嘅調平會，亦都係新嘅，噉你開頭乜都冇嘅時候，要整一個秘書處去做。
誒註冊或者係誒操手或者係誒誒業界嘅誒提升資力各樣嘅工作，在在都係需要人手嘅。咁政府既然你係可以推動呢個行業去到立法，係咪可以攞一個即係總子基金出嚟，即係畀佢？
去開展個工作咧。第二就係李生就話大學會同調評會嗰度大家溝通，但係我我覺得你唔可以就咁留翻大學同埋一個即係仲未有法定地位嘅調評會，大家去去相處嘅，即係政府自己係要做一啲誒中間人嘅工作，去確保。
起碼確保大學而家開嘅課程同將來規管業界註冊嘅團體，大家會唔會係即係講緊同一樣嘢？否則咧就會有人交咗學費讀完曬，誒誒。
唔知有有啲長有啲短嘅課程，但係將來就係得唔到嗰個執業嘅資格，咁咪到時又有出嚟，又有人出嚟申訴㗎啦。
李生，或者你答咗第一條關於總資基金嗰樣？啊，主席係多謝議員提問啊！啊，當然啊，第一就係頭先啊，大家都聽到就係呢一個啊調平會咧，係一個啊私人機構嚟嘅，政府係冇參與，係一個一個獨立嘅機構嚟嘅。咁關於佢嗰個運作啊，同埋資金嘅問題咧。
如果佢哋有需要，等於好多其他嘅誒機構一樣，佢哋都可以同政府大家係有個溝通。如果嘅需要嘅話，咁咪根據嗰啲渠道，我哋都可以考慮。但問題就係誒，當然我冇辦法喺度向大家話係得與唔得。咁呢個就係仲要需要係知道實質上工作同埋需要係幾。
幾多先？同埋咧有個申請，然後大家先至考慮。咁呢個就係一個一般嘅程序去做。咁當然，如果係覺得個需要係好急嘅，咁變咗睇下我哋可唔可以特事特辦。咁但係呢個係另一件事嚇。咁誒，關於係。
政府當然啦，我哋係啊喺特別，我哋喺度政先，我哋都希望係確保嗰個溝通係渠道喺度，同埋咧就係有有有溝通噉樣。咁如果係有需要，我哋作為係誒。
推動呢一個調解嘅話咧，我哋當然係係可以。
係幫助。
調評會同埋係學業學啊大學啊或者其他啲機構咧，佢哋有一個密切嘅誒。
聯絡同埋知道大家需要乜嘢，但係最重要一樣嘢就係。
頭頭先提到就係話係可唔可以確保佢哋有啲乜嘢嘅地位？如果讀完嗰個啊嗰個課程嘅時候，但呢個咧一定要當然係要調平會自己定咗嗰個嗰個需要係乜嘢先。咁而家呢一步一步去做，我諗係一定會係有個溝通，同埋啊，好似頭先咁講，我哋都係將啊。
梁議員上次提嗰個意見咧，交咗畀調評會，咁呢個亦都會考慮在內㗎嘛。係啊，主席，我係好明白咧，唔會話即係交咗學費上完四十個鐘咧，一定係攞到一個執業資格。正正係咁咧，即係如果嗰個課程調評會都覺得喂唔掂㗎喎，你未讀夠個範圍唔夠喎，噉就要公開話畀報名。
嘅學生聽嗱，你當興趣好啦，讀完你就學識咗呢樣嘢，但係你係執唔到業嘅噉，即係等學生報名之前係會知識佢將來係咪有一個誒事業係可以開展噉。我我希望呢個真係做到唔好等同學有任何誤會，因為呢啲事情咧，我哋以前。
見過誒，尤其是而家咁多副學士學位出現，噉就有一啲專業學院咧，就直情係教護理添啊，教院嗰個專業團體唔肯承認，到最後即係班學生又係即係有一屆嘅學生要特事特辦，噉我都唔希望成日都出現呢啲特事特辦嘅情。
情況啦，咁所以即係，I I hope Mr. John Butch would also the。
aware of the courses being offered in the tertiary education institute and start communicating with them and and actually any tertiary education institute before they offer any courses on this subject should should be informed by the government that they should approach Hong Kong Mail for.
或的qualification，或future accreditation of the course。
I think there are two questions, Mr. Butch. First of all, is there enough funding and resources for Hong Kong MRO to start doing what it's supposed to do? And secondly, is accreditation issue? Yes, Mr. Chairman, can I? I'll deal with the funding point.
Certainly, the previous S.J. was very keen and told me on many occasions that this was to be an industry-led, self-funding body, and I took that to heart greatly. And I would have thought that you, the lookers after the public purse, would be pleased that we've taken that to heart and that we aren't seeking any.
Public funding, it's very much back of the envelope stuff at the present moment. But you have seen the numbers of people that are in the three of the founding bodies, and we haven't, of course, counted the bar as well, who haven't got an accreditation body, but do through Cedar, another well-known body, have.
Quite a few hundred mediators as well. So we are hopeful that quite a lot of people will come along and pay the annual subscription, which will be pitching at around nine hundred dollars. And if my sums are right, that should ensure that we have sufficient funding. So.
At the present moment, I don't plan to apply for for funding, and that the whoever is the party who, in the end of the day, is going to be the temporary secretariat for this body, I think that you know they will have to wait a little while for the money until until the annual.
Subscription start flowing in, but certainly on our market research that we've done.
There is a great deal of interest with regard to Hong Kong Mall, and I think that I've lived in Hong Kong for thirty-four years. I know Hong Kong people love qualifications, and it is highly likely that they will apply to Hong Kong Mall because the support that has been given to Hong Kong Mall by.
Not only the administration, but also the judiciary. Johnson Lam, for example, who is a very highly respected judge, as I'm sure you're all aware, has been very, very involved in the various committees that I've been sitting at. He sits also on the accreditation committee of the HKIC, and I.
我見到司法，直至首席大法官，都有HKML的支持。所以我希望，可能不是我，但我希望我的同僚在五年後會來到這個委員會，要求有關法律的支援。
因為它已經是成功故事，但我想它成為成功故事，因為香港的認證機構的 proliferation 是不滿意的，而且有太多太多的人稱自己是認證機構，因為我們的地理位置，地理位置。
Hong Kong, a small place, lots of people. That we have the potential of doing something which very few other countries in the world have been able to do, which is create this overarching premier accreditation body. And I am excited by it. And I am certainly, and my fellow directors as well are excited by it to take on this.
Challenge, because I think it would be very good for Hong Kong. So that's the self-funding side. With regard to Ms Ho's points, and I wholly agree with her, with regard to that we do not want to have false expectations. I have to say that there is a great deal of interest in mediation.
但係，唔係夠多調解人嚟到。
to make， there are very few very few full-time mediators in Hong Kong.
And I don't think that there will be that many full-time mediators in Hong Kong.
我諗，好多人都上課程。
Are not planning to be mediators. I think a lot of them attained.
courses because they want to know more about mediation, or they're parties they're going to be representing parties before mediations.
But I think what we've got to be very careful about, and certainly in the HKIC, we are we certainly never never say to anyone that just because you're an accredited mediator that you're going to have a full-time job as a mediator the next day. And I think that we have to be careful that you know we don't over-qualify a huge number of people.
喺喺嘅調解界。
They're being believing that by investing that money that they will get a great amount of of work the next day. No, I don't think that's going to happen. But there is no doubt there's a great deal of interest in mediation, and certainly someone who is very interested in mediation. I think it's wonderful that all these people are coming forward.
We in the HKIC and in the HKML, and I think the HKML will be. You got to remember, there's quite a lot of.
By the founder members, quite a lot of experience now in the accreditation of mediators. Will and have worked with the universities. Certainly, many many courses in HKIAC and in the Law Society are courses run by the university, and that the universities have.
Hong Kong, and so we are very aware that we need to work with the universities and that they they know the standards that are required, and to ensure that those that do attend these courses and invest time and money will be accredited.
所以，我我 take your point， Miss Ho， and and we are aware of it， and we have been aware of it， and we will continue to be aware of it。Thank you， Mr. Tan Yu Zhong Yip。誒，關於調解呢嗰啲方面，誒用通過調解方式嚟處理一啲誒紛爭，即係唔一定要去法庭嗰個訴訟。我覺得呢個推
仲係係誒非常之好嘅，咁誒對於調解員咧，誒我相信，因為現時嚟講個數目應該夠嘅，因為呢個工作其實喺香港仲，我個相信係有待努力去宣傳推廣，啊，因為好多人都係誒未必誒認識或者。
未必誒，一定想用呢個方式，寧願等法院去判噉。
噉我自己嗰個認識咧，就係我見有啲律師嘅朋友，佢哋去考呢個攞呢個調解員嗰個資格咧，就佢哋翻嚟講到話啊，雖然上完曬課之後咧，但係要攞到個資格要考試咧，都唔係咁容易嘅啊，都要誒幾經努力先至攞得到。
係。
誒，相反有啲唔係律師背景嗰啲，啊，佢又考得到。
咁所以就誒都唔一定話邊類人，但係我亦都發覺咧，有啲人攞到個資格，佢係屬於認識嘅啫。佢知道下嗰個係咩一回事，有啲咩嘢可以幫到佢，即係攞到呢個知識之後，幫助到佢日常嘅工作，包括有啲區員佢都去考嘅，去試下嘅啊。噉啊～
誒噉，佢覺得有好處嘅，即係以後幫助佢誒處理真係有啲咩嘅個案嘅時候咧，係有一個幫助。
咁噉，所以佢又唔一定攞嚟即係執誒，攞嚟誒當係一種職業啊，或者係誒咩嘅。噉我就覺得而家噉樣落去咧，就應該嚇特別有調評會之後咧，步步就要確立起嚟，因為有喺誒調解裏邊咧有好多不同嘅個案，即係點樣能夠。
誒一路不斷啲調解員積累經驗，其實最緊要經驗嘅嚇，咁而且咧誒，因為個個個案係係好唔同嘅，噉你亦都冇可能你熟悉曬所有嘢嚇。
即係律師都有，有佢自己選擇，佢自己嗰個。
誒，屬於想想係誒做邊類嘅嘅嘅個案，噉啊有啲可能對家庭嗰啲嘢就特別熟悉嘅嚇誒，或者有啲啊同經濟啊或者商業啊嗰啲噉嘅，咁所以我覺得佢就應該係會逐步啊提高個水平，點樣去誒？
嚟誒能夠誒有更多富有經驗，或者慢慢走去誒專門啲嘅誒嘅嘅嘅做法。咁呢啲，我相信都係應該係未來咧，有調平會出現之後咧，我希望佢可以可以誒確立到一支噉嘅隊伍噉。
從而咧，就會畀到一啲信心，嗰啲嘅。
誒，當事人咁即係覺得啊，係喎啊，原來呢啲人都對呢啲嘅調解員都係好好有水平，可以幫助我解決問題嘅。咁咁慢慢又確立咗個嗰個信任，咁亦都可以幫助去解決啊。我哋嗰個原先誒呢個調解條例嗰個目的嚇。
噉我我覺得誒應該可以一齊努力喺呢個方向去做啊！
我呢個係個意見嚟嘅。
啊，李生有冇嘢想？啊，主席，啊，好多謝譚議員意見，我哋一定會，啊。
跟住聽到跟住去做噉樣嚇，依個亦都係我哋認同嘅意見嚇。
Mr. Budge，Would you like to?
response.
with Mr Tam and there's a great deal of interest in Hong Kong. I think we're still.
In his early days, it's I don't think we can quite call it a profession, but it's an area which is is growing and there's a great deal of interest. We already have a substantial body of family mediators in Hong Kong, and in fact, if you look at the history of mediation, the mediation movement in Hong Kong, it affects.
started off in the family area, and is growing a bit, then into construction, and then there was a great void in the middle where there wasn't too much mediation going on, and we've had to do quite a lot of catch up, and Hong Kong's really
taking it on board very much after the civil litigation proposals for for change and and also to make mediation part and parcel of of the litigation process of the court process should I say so we're still early we're still early days yet I mean Hong Kong Mall certainly I take
Mr Tam's helpful comments and Ms Ho's helpful comments, and we will certainly bear those in mind. And as I said earlier, I think hopefully all of you share with me the view that that Hong Kong Mall will be a success, and that if it is a success, as I said, the obvious step forward is that.
That it will become a statutory body with with statutory powers, but at the present moment it's it's very much we have to win hearts and minds, and to show that that we are a body an an inclusive body, but also in many ways an exclusive body. We can't allow any Tom, Dick and Harry to to apply.
Who goes on a half an hour course or not maybe half a day course to become a mediator? We have to have recognised standards. And this body, I have to point out, and I would like to underline, and I've said this on so many cases.
Hong Kong will be a regulator. Its job is to look after standards and discipline. It's not in any way dealing with promotion of mediation. There are many other bodies that will be dealing with promotion. We will be very much a standards body.
Thank you, Mr. Budget。啊，梁美芬議員。
嗯，多謝啊！咁多位可以出席今日嘅會議啊。我諗咧調解咧係我哋一直希望喺香港推動，我哋好希望佢成功。
亦都係誒，我相信呢個係符合公眾嘅利益㗎。
咁咧，但係即係頭先提到咧，誒，同事講阿譚議員講咧，即係有啲律師可能反為讀得唔好，有啲唔係律師嘅讀得好或者讀到咧。我我會理解，因為我諗咧調解咧，佢唔係純粹咧可以用法律。
就調解到佢，可能包括其他好多嘅專業，所以咧家事或者金融調解咧，佢係配合埋其他喺雙方當事人咧嗰個嘅誒心態去進行到一個達成到一個協議。調解係一個自願嘅，咁所以喺我過往嘅經驗咧。
誒好多時調解成功咧，係需要一個好成熟，佢自己對即係生命生活都有一定嘅理解，佢好容易理理解到雙方嗰個分歧，從而令到佢哋願意咧係調解成功。
所以喺呢一方面咧，即係我我自己咧就好關心咧，就係嗰個課程嘅設計。
嗱，我我上次都有提到咧，我自己都喺城市大學喺法律學院嗰度教書。
誒就舉城市大學為一個例子咧，佢哋喺嗰個誒alternative dispute resolution嘅嘅嘅課程裏邊係走得好前喺誒仲裁同埋調解方面咧，亦都係誒有好多喺國際上嘅一啲嘅誒。
嗰個嘅課程啊，專家都有嚟參與去去去講。而另外兩間大學，我知道之後亦都有喺呢啲嘅，即係誒誒調解嘅課程或者係其他咧，佢哋亦都開始有啲係有開啓。噉我就好關心咧，喺你哋。
嗰個課程設計去確保誒一個專業嘅水準。頭先啊啊，Mr. Butch講。
同埋咧，嗰個嘅誒。
嗰個嘅資格嘅承認。
成個嘅誒課程，同埋嗰啲係乜嘢人去開辦呢個課程？
點樣去配合？有一啲係喺現時調平會成立之前，其實已經走得好前。特別係大學，我覺得係一啲係認可嘅大學，甚至係法學院幾家。你哋係點樣去將呢一啲有經驗嘅係吸納咗？
喺你哋而家開啓，譬如你哋點樣去？你話係一個regulator係係係係係管理成個呢一個調解嘅發展課程資格嘅審核點樣去令到呢一啲唔同嘅持份者佢哋係可以參與，從而佢哋除咗。
參與之外咧，其實亦都應該咧係有一啲可能係好似我哋喺課程裏邊咧都會係自動佢係可以獲得承認，因為佢唔係一種坊間嘅一個課程。咁呢一啲喺大學或者認可嘅教育機構同誒坊間裏邊，而家你哋考慮再去。
提供畀公眾話去誒攻讀嘅調解課程嗰個嘅合作係點樣咧？嗰個資格嘅認可係點咧？你哋嗰啲嘅誒委員會裏面有冇吸納咗呢啲有經驗，專門喺大學負責呢種課程嘅嗰啲嘅負責人？
喺裡面咧。
誒或者我請調評會嘅主席啊，Mr. Butt。
誒回應啊！
Mr. Butz. Yes, Mr. Chairman, Ms. Lund, thank you for your comments.
Miss Lung, we have at present just four founder members, but we intend to be inviting other members to to join the Hong Kong Mall, and we already have quite a substantial amount, I think, of experience on our committee.
Let me just point out my own experience in this area. I mentioned earlier, I have been sitting on the Hong Kong International Arbitration Centre Mediation Accreditation Committee. That's a rather large mouthful, but I have been involved in the accreditation of mediation courses now for 15.
years, and I have been chairing the mediation accreditation committee of HKIC for almost six years. So I would say that I know a little bit about this area, and I would have thought that we have certainly in the mediation accreditation committee of HKIC.
Been accrediting courses from the universities for many many years, and have worked very closely with those universities, and we will continue to do so. And so, therefore, I I don't think that the City University, your institution, or anything any of the other institutions that we work with, Hong Kong, Hong Kong University.
Space. We've worked with Chinese university. We have should have any concerns that we will not take into consideration the same type of criteria that we have in the past, and that we will work very closely with them. So I would like to.
Put your heart at ease on that particular area.
And we certainly been working very closely in the various committees that that I've been involved in with people like Professor Naja Alexander who used to be one of your colleagues at City University, now at Xiuyan University, who is a world expert in this area. So I think that that we are, I think we do.
have the experience, and we've we will be using. We will not be
reinventing the wheel in this area. We will be using similar standards that we have used in the in the various bodies in the Hong Kong Mall.
嗯，我想即係問下咧，頭先我提到咧，就係話，嗯，嗰啲大學嘅課程，佢哋係係正規嘅課程，係會唔會已經係譬如係免收某一啲嘅學分，有冇要過去到咁即係誒去到咁詳細去考慮呢個問題啦？因為咧誒，我都喺大。
學差唔多二十年，即係教學課程嘅設計同埋成個嗰個點樣去啊完成一個課程咧，其實佢都係有一套嘅。咁譬如誒，而家喺誒Hong Kong Model，佢係你哋而家係用一個有限公司，噉你哋係點樣？
去推動呢一樣嘢，係定係頭先你提到，你話都會有一啲個別係喺大學可能教過嘅一啲同事喺裏邊，但係同你正式去即係開啟呢個合作嘅關係咧，係誒始終係唔同嘅。你個別一個一個成員係，譬如我都同政府。
府佢哋嗰個誒steering committee傾過，我亦都同有啲大學佢哋係課程嘅主任傾過。咁可能喺個別諮詢，你哋係有，但係你哋係誒，我覺得現有嘅資源嘅大學全部都係Ugc分特嚇，有好多呢一啲嘅誒應該。
咧唔好嗱，點解我哋有今日嘅會咧？因為上次其實另外一啲同事都提到，我哋唔希望咧調平會咧會重到中醫。
中醫學界嘅一個問題嗱，呢個咧，我頭先舉例子係大學啫。但係其實上次同事提到係坊間，可能仲有好多係係舉辦調解嘅課程。中醫出現嘅問題後屘喺呢一度嚟咗，沒完沒了，就係好多好多相關佢哋。
係持份者嘅人就投訴示威噉，跟住我哋開咗好多次聆訊，佢哋其實到而家都仲未停，就係話咧，因為我哋反想推動反圍，就排除咗好多可能。佢哋係老中醫，好多有資格嘅。噉我覺得而家因為你哋係用有限公司，就。
亦都唔係一個誒誒大學啊，或者公營機構咁喺呢個階段咧，我哋喺立法會係好希望調解係成功，所以將所有呢一啲嘅經驗，你能夠可以説服到，而家你哋呢一套就係。
誒海納百川者，you you already consider all these related talents in mediation。
In your company or your group, because if you just mention one or two name, yes, I know they are already in the mediation circle. But it is very different from absorbing all the existing stakeholders as well as the experience entities. And we we really want to avoid the situation.
that has arisen from the Chinese medicine experience.
Mr. Justice.
Thank you. It's an area traditional Chinese medicine is not an area that I know anything about, but I, I can see that you are concerned. We must, we are.
一 body that is trying to be as inclusive as possible.
At the same time, we have this other part of our role, which is to ensure standards. And I'm sure that you, this group here, will be the first to agree with me that we have got to protect standards, because a lot of these mediators will be facing up to the general public.
and we must ensure that they are properly qualified.
There is already quite a body of experience with regard to accreditation of mediators in Hong Kong. We also are very aware of the good work that's being done by the tertiary institutions, and we will certainly take into consideration the views of the tertiary institution. But at the same time, we must take into consideration the views of of of of
the industry generally, and so there's quite a lot of tension here that we've got to ensure that that we are
Listening to all the various stakeholders, and it will not be an easy job. But we will do our best, because we don't have statutory backing, and I'm not asking for statutory backing. We but we need to take it a step at a time. We hope that we will get a body of mediators to join HKMRL.
and。
In time, this will be the premier accreditation body in Hong Kong. 主席，我要問一問。係，梁偉文議員。係啊，誒，正正其實我哋就係關心嗰個standard。
即係喺誒嗰個標準嗰個問題上咧，即係我係誒誒點解我要噉樣提咧？其實嗱，我自己咧就唔係教調解嘅課程嘅嚇，我係睇到喺誒大學幾個課程咧。
佢哋其實係好有經驗。
噉，我認為咧嗱，即係你頭先嘅答覆咧，即係誒好坦白講，我覺得有啲開始學好似政府啦。I will consider誒呢個喺我哋嚟講係唔唔係一個滿意嘅答案。我哋希望嘅係具體咧，起碼我諗三間大學法學院佢哋如果有。
有開辦。
有開辦調解或者alternative dispute resolution嘅課程，佢哋嘅誒一啲負責嘅或者佢哋負責嘅教授。
我認為咧，你哋應該吸納佢哋喺裏面，因為咧，佢哋已經係經過好多年。
嘅課程嘅開辦，香港嘅人嚟參讀去參加，有啲係攞著攞埋學位。佢哋嘅需要點樣設計，點樣先至係真係可以係一個專業嘅一個訓練？我認為咧，嗰個唔係純粹就咁consider consider咧，你就冇。
將而家香港嗰個經驗咧，真係完全係可以包攬在裏邊。我認為你哋喺開辦課程裏邊嘅過程個程序上咧，係應該係起碼係要邀請呢啲負責嘅，佢係喺呢一方面好有經驗嘅，係喺你哋嗰個。
課程。
開啓嘅時候，因為你開啓嘅時候，我唔知你會唔會係會同一間大學掛鈎，或者你話頭先你提到誒有啲叫做校外課程嘅，噉你都要有一個具體嘅要睇到，即係你哋點解係會咁嗱？因為我哋推動呢樣嘢咧，就唔係純粹係畀一個好細嘅group，而係我哋係希
希望整體香港社會，佢最後係獲益而係最有水準、最好嘅課程。
出嚟嘅，佢亦都係即係。頭先我講調解，真係唔係一個新啱啱新畢業嘅人，佢可能係一就做到個成功嘅調解員。佢仲要配合好多佢自己個人經驗嘅因素。咁呢一啲，你點樣可以令到？因為我哋喺立法會，我哋係鼓勵啲人添，即係我自己就即係知道好多人。
人係打唔起官司，佢能夠嘅，譬如金融調解，就係我哋喺雷曼個專責委員會裏面慢慢係可以形成出嚟。最後嘅希望政府就做咗一個金融調解，係因為打官司佢哋打唔起嚇。咁當我哋推動嘅時候，我哋希望呢一樣嘢係令我哋覺得舒服嘅。你哋做嘅時候。
個透明度同埋嗰個闊度係符合到香港，同埋吸納到整體，其實而家有嘅經驗喺度。
即係嗰個唔可以就咁考慮嘅，因為呢樣嘢唔係就噉你睇出邊一個機構，係我哋經過好多年喺立法會亦都推動，政府又推動一齊推動嘅一個事情嚟嘅。
都係啦，冇問題。Mr. Budget, any any further? Yes, Mr. Leana, I hear you. Your points. Let me just just step back a little.
With this body, Hong Kong will not be offering courses. I mean, we are an accreditation body. We are not offering courses. We are not doing anything different than what the the mediation accreditation bodies of the of the of the of the bodies that we're looking at in the founder members.
律師公會和我們自己以及律師業。
It's not our job to provide courses. Our job will be to accredit courses, and we already have got, I think, already got a lot of knowledge through both. Certainly, the Law Society who, who very much have have followed the HKIC's model.
Over the last 15 years, so your institution, the City University, also the other universities, well know the standards that we've been looking for and have been very helpful in setting those standards. So I'm, I don't think that you need worry that we're going to
Create a whole new body of standards on day one. That's certainly, as the chairman, I mean, I'm only the chairman. I'm not can't speak for the whole board. That we will not be reinventing the wheel. So I don't think that that you
Your body should be in any way. Your university should be in any way concerned that with the creation of Hong Kong Mall, that courses that have been previously accredited by, say the HKIC, will not be accredited after they apply in the new year for accreditation. So I think we've already, you know, we're not.
reinventing the wheel. I mean, you're
Your people like Mr. Beckett. I mean, we we we know him and and we've worked with him. And so I don't I don't I wouldn't be concerned that we're going to
going to say that there's this whole new body of standards because we don't want to do that. We want to try to be as inclusive as possible, at the same time as I keep on saying to keep up standards and be transparent in the process as well.係唔好意思，主席，我仲有少追問。其實誒，頭先我講清楚，唔係某一間。
係。
學校嗰個問題，而係頭先咧，你講到一樣嘢，我就想誒問落去，即係話咧，你哋唔會負責課程，噉係咪即係又係交翻畀坊間？
係佢哋可以隨便去開辦咧？
我認為一個簡單的yes or no會。
They can offer the courses and we can accredit them. We will look at them and whether they're up to our standards, we will accredit them.
即係話，你哋會係睇唔同嘅課程，你哋就會去審核下嗰啲課程嘅水準。完之後咧，就先即係話所譬如譬如，即係我簡單講，譬如我有朋友或者有一啲人，佢哋咧一啲機構，佢有興趣，佢就可以成立一個噉就可以咧。如果
佢自己有能力就可以開辦呢啲課程，最主要個結果係你哋去睇佢訓練出嚟嘅人最後嗰個質素，定係佢開辦嘅時候，你都係應該有少少要求。即係我我想了解呢一方面係。
係點嘅情況？即係而家你哋嗰個睇法。
我。
I've been working on the on the HK Mall website, and the the standards that we are going to be putting in place are will be exactly the same.
standards as in the HKIC website. So if you just go and have a look at the HKIC website, you will get an idea of where we're going on this matter. And we will not, I repeat, we will not be offering courses. We will merely accrediting those courses. So if your friends put together a course which is up to the
Standard that we are expecting, we will accredit it, and those people who go on that course will be able to get the accreditation for what we call stage one, and then there will be a common exam, a common assessment called stage two. These will be exactly the same as we've been doing for many years.
在香港。
to to ensure that that people not only go through the
the academic side of the of the course, the the forty hour course, I'm talking of general mediators, but will thereafter be assessed, and and as Mr. Tan said, he's no longer with us, that not everybody who is assessed passes the assessment. Again, we don't want a situation where 100% of people pass.
那會指示我，那個考驗太容易。我們要確保適當的標準被維持。
Thank you, Mr. Budge.
啊，主席，再再問多個問題，即係頭先好清楚，即係話咧開辦課程就，如果即係任何機構、任何人，佢想佢都可以。其實而家係應該話開辦課程，佢冇門檻。
只係喺最後讀完之後，會唔會accredit？嗰度係有一個門檻喺度，係咪咁？
好清楚。
啊！
I'm really not quite sure, Miss Lang, where you're coming from.
我話：，我話，
那個措施會有要。
People that know what they're doing. We will expect not only the materials. We will we will examine the.
The various slots during the 40-hour course that will be done, we will expect experienced tutors. We will expect certainly a very experienced course director. We will expect high standards of those that provide courses. So again, we know. Sorry, I think I think Mr. Batch. Actually, what I'm
講緊 about this。
從最開始，其實係沒有限制，對任何可能對我們課程感興趣的人。係咪正確？我們不是在談論課程的內容，因為我們關心的是，如果有人在香港，如果他們發現這個是熱門趨勢。
They might consider to.
open certain kind of training house and then they will offer courses. So I am asking, actually, right now we don't have any kind of barrier or limitation or rules as to who is to open courses in this regard. That is what I am asking, not the content of the course. That is the second stage.
Whether you are critic or whether they reach the standard, this is another matter. You know, Hong Kong, everything, everyone would do advertisement for any kind of market.
commercial opportunities， if they can see。
Thank you.
Mr. Chairman, yes, Mr. Budge, just, yeah.
嗯。
Yes, I mean we live in an entrepreneurial society in Hong Kong. If if these people have got the various standards, then they could set up a court because there is no legislation in Hong Kong stopping people from doing it.
Okay.
O.K.啊。
張文悦，阿張文全耀，係多謝主席。
就誒。
呢個調平會咧，我相信佢嗰個即係要做嘅嘢好多，可以話嚇任重任重道遠。因為我哋都希望呢個調平嘅工作咧就係成功，同埋亦都係廣受即係誒我哋嗰個接受，即係香港嘅接受。
咁咧就誒。
喺評定嗰個資格同埋水平嗰方面咧，就我相信調評會咧，即係亦都會喺呢方面咧，就係誒做好多工作。
噉啊喺制定嗰方面咧，就係誒，我相信即係誒。
因為咧，嗰個調平個調平員咧，而家頭先聽講咧，即係即係都唔會有太多全職嘅。咁即係好多誒嗰個誒有興趣係參與喺個調平作為調平員嘅方面咧，即係好多時候咧就係都可能自己有正職噉，所以喺啊。
誒，如果係喺個即係可以承認到。
誒一個調平員個資格方面咧，喺人數方面咧，可能係雖然我而家睇到，可能就係淨係呢三個咧都有差唔多成二千人。
咁但係足唔足夠咧？當然要睇嗰個，即係係咪接受嘅程度。
我我想講一樣嘢咧，就係因為誒，即係本身我業界都瞭解過咧，就喺建築測量方面咧，即係涉及即係過去咧好多關於建築誒工程嘅合同嘅糾紛，或者喺屋宇方面嘅有啲誒，因為各方面嘅事宜嘅糾紛噉。
我哋都有唔少嘅業界嘅都參與呢個調平嗰個工作。
誒有一樣嘢咧，頭先我都好誒開心聽到咧，就係其實即係個調平會方面咧，就會廣納其他而家現有嗰個喺呢個方面嘅。
誒誒或者一啲組織架構嘅意見，因為咧我同一部分我哋業界最初傾咧，佢哋咧就有意見咧，因為呢個調評會咧本身個創會嗰個誒成員咧即係四位，噉我都理解咧，即係你冇得太多。
噉啊，即係喺呢個我哋學會啊，或者喺建築測量方面咧，會畀一個感覺咧，或者部分人感覺咧，會唔會呢個調平咧，將來做咧就係最主要咧，就係令到感覺咧，就係將其他而家或者過去其他唔係呢啲四個創會會員嗰啲咧。
誒嗰啲組織啊，或者係參與者咧，就係拒之門外。咁呢樣嘢，我相信就唔會嘅。但係都希望咧喺個調評會方面咧，就係喺呢方面咧多溝通做啲工作。噉啊誒，我亦都即係盡量去，因為我參與咗呢個小組咧，係同我哋業界方面咧，儘量係可以。
以解釋翻噉啊！喺呢方面咧，我諗即係希望咧喺制定個水平方面咧，因為調平可能涉涉及嘅事宜咧係好廣泛，咁又唔各方面嘅人才都需要噉啊。溝通方面啊，或者係點樣令到佢可能成為其中一份子方面咧？呢個調平會方面嘅工作咧，就係。
嚟都艱巨，但係希望咧，我佢哋都會喺呢方面咧，儘量可以令到誒，即係大家個意見咧，都可能係有機會發表到。噉啊，呢個對將來呢個調平方面嘅工作嘅成功同埋吸引嚇，我哋誒水平高嘅調平員方面咧。
參與咧就誒都誒可以做到好多功夫，噉啊，多謝主席。
Mr. Butch, would you like to respond? Yes, Mr. Chair, thank you for your comments.
I'm I'm well aware there's a sort of perception, and I've gone out of my way to try to ensure that that's not true. That this is a a legal body, and it's been rather taken on by the lawyers. That's not true. I certainly
I had a very interesting experience earlier in the week. On Tuesday of this week, we had another meeting of the Mediation Accreditation Committee of HKIC, and the thirty-two applicants for general membership. And I was delighted and pleased to.
見到，係的確，我哋嘅法律界嘅人，係非常之少。
and and various other disciplines, teachers, and I thought this is just wonderful that that all these people have attended these courses, and have gone through the assessments and and were accredited by my body, and and I thought this is great. This is showing that that that really this is.
一industry。
which has got a lot of of different specialisations and and people from lots of walks of life coming forward, and I hear about the surveyors. There are many surveyors who are already on the the panel, the HKIC, and
Again, I hope that they will, when eventually we're ready to go, will apply to become HKMall accredited mediators, and and also I'm aware that the the savers also want to get involved with Hong Kong Mall, and I welcome that.
所以，我認為建築業界，一啲好嘅工作已經做咗，喺調解服務方面，建築業界，我盼望調解會繼續係一個好有用嘅工具，解決建築爭議喺未來。
多謝Mr. But梁美芬議員第二輪。誒，我我諗咧，即係頭先同啊Mr. But嗰個頭誒，即係好清楚啦。即係其實任何即係佢有能力或者佢有興趣，可能有一啲人噉，佢認為係誒商機或者有興趣都好啦，佢都可以開辦呢啲課程。咁咧，我只係想提出咧，就係將。
將來咧，因為我哋係希望推廣調解嘅，我相信咧，即係我哋希望呢一樣嘢將來咧係成功，就少啲投訴。咁喺呢啲舉辦課程嗰度咧，如果你哋係推廣調解嘅同事，因為可能坊間就會出現好多呢一啲提供調解課程都唔出奇嘅，因為係。
唔需要有，亦都唔需要有啲咩專業背景都可以去報讀㗎嘛。咁咧都要提一提，即係話咧，即係到最後你可能係要有咩要求，叫佢自己，即係好似即係消費者權一樣啦嚇。因為其實最大問題就出至於將來有好會唔會好多宣傳嗰啲宣傳係。
係誒，對於公眾去理解佢去去報讀同埋去做嗰樣，最後佢仲能夠做到咧？好似同事講話期望管理噉，你嘅期望管理咧就唔係就噉話就咁管理，而係我哋當我哋推廣調解嘅時候，就可能同時咧要考慮到呢一點，噉就唔會太濫。
而同時咧，去報讀咗嘅人，佢亦都清楚呢樣嘢係有要求，要提醒佢哋咯，嚇，因為到時候佢亦都係一個消費者嚟㗎啦，嚇，噉我哋儘量希望避免呢啲嘅發生，噉我都希望咧，將呢個意見提出嘅。多謝梁美芬，你想唔想佢再補充？唔使㗎。Thank you。仲有冇其他議員想？
提問啊！
如果冇嘅話，誒，我哋誒或者睇一睇嗰個誒。
二零一二年啊，第一百六十七號法律公告，誒嗰個文件。
我哋剩係我，你識。
Yeah, Mr. Budge, you could stay on if you want to, but thank you very much for attending, especially so early in the morning, and thank you for for your answers to to the members' questions. We're going to move on to the looking at the commencement notice now.
所以，我我 may leave， or you wish you may if you want to.
Thank you very much, and thank you very much to members as well.
嗱，個文件本身就好簡單啦，就係一個生效日期嘅公告啦，就係指定二零一三年一月一號咧，係為該條例即係調解條例咧，係誒開始實施嘅日期嘅。大家委員有冇咩誒問題或者意見？
係，如果冇嘅話咧，噉我就會向。
啊！呢個啊內務委員會咧提交我哋誒小組委員會嘅一個報告啦，噉就誒嗰個誒時間表咧啊，秘書處都已經誒係好啊，或者你講講個秘書誒嗰個時間表。
係，都係主席就誒，如果委員會已經係完成嗰個審議工作咧，咁因為誒先前啊，主席已經喺立法會大會咧將嗰個審議期咧係延展到十二月十二號嘅。
咁如果議員係想就住呢一個誒公告係提出修訂咧，嗰個畀預告嗰個誒誒限期咧就係十二月五號。咁而頭先阿主席都提過咧，就誒佢將會喺十一月三十號咧就向內會提交一個誒呢個委員會嗰個正式嘅書面報告嘅。多謝主席。
係，如果冇其他事項，我宣告散會。
多謝大家，thank you。